Guide to the Manumit School Collection TAM.528
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Manumit School Collection
circa 1920s-2010s
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Speer, R. Michael
Fincke, William Mann
Dretzin, Barbara Dutton
TAM.528
2 Linear Feet in two manuscript boxes, one folder, and one oversize flat box.
Manumit School was a Christian socialist school in Pawling, NY, 1924-1943, then in Bristol, PA, 1944-1958. The collection is an assembled collection containing printed ephemera, correspondence, writings of the School's director (1933-1958), William Mann Fincke, who was a son of the co-founders, Reverend William Mann Fincke (d. 1927) and Helen Harden Fincke; a CD containing material from the website "Manumit School" devoted to its history, and photographs of students and life at the school.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Robert Michael (Mike) Speer in 2009; additional materials were donated by Speer in 2011, 2014, and 2016, and by Barbara Dutton Dretzin in 2013. The accession numbers associated with these gifts are 2010.027, 2011.148, 2013.016, 2014.104, and 2016.019.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically.
Historical/Biographical Note
Manumit School was a Christian socialist co-educational, elementary, non-denominational, boarding school in Pawling, NY, 1924-1943, then in Bristol, PA, 1944-1958. In 1924, Rev. William Mann Fincke and his wife, Helen Hamlin, founded Manumit as an elementary level, co-educational, boarding school on a working farm in Pawling, NY. In 1926, Henry I. Lineman became interim Director upon illness of Rev. Fincke, who died in 1927. In 1927-1928 Nellie M. Seeds became Director, Seeds resigned in 1933 and joined the New York State Education Department. In 1933, William Mann Fincke, the son of Fincke and Hamlin, assumed Co-Directorship, with wife, Mildred Gignoux By 1938-1939 the Progressive Schools' Committee for Refugee Children formed under leadership of Mildred and William Fincke. In 1944, Manumit moved to Bristol, Bensalem Township, Bucks County, PA. The first full high school graduation occurred in 1951. During this period, Benjamin ("Ben") C. G. Fincke [son of founders], with wife, Magda, were Co-Director, from 1947-1954, until replaced by John A. Lindhof. In 1956, external attacks on the school began, due to it being an interracial school, which led to the school closure in 1958. In the 2000s, alumni of the school began holding reunions and symposiums, resulting in additional materials in this collection.
Custodial History
The archived website was migrated from the California Digital Library's Web Archiving Service to the Internet Archive's Archive-It Service in November 2015. The link to California Digital Library was removed in October 2017.
Related Archival Materials
An archived version of the website can be found here: http://webarchives.cdlib.org/site/sw15d8nk00
Scope and Contents
The collection is an artificial grouping of records, printed ephemera, three issues of The Manuscript, and writings of the Director, 1933-1958, William Mann Fincke, who was a son of the co-founders, Reverend William Mann Fincke and Helen Harden Fincke. There is significant amount of correspondence in the collection, including letters to Benjamin and Magda Fincke; a chronology and several histories of Manumit; a CD containing material from the website "Manumit School" devoted to its history, and selected email exchanges from 2005-2009 between alumni; also included are copies of some materials from the New York Public Library. A second CD contains the proceedings of a Manumit School Symposium of Jul 9, 2011. The collection also contains many photographs, including photographs of the groups, students, and programing. In addition, there is an oversized book of illustrated stories written by Manumit School students who were around high school age during World War II.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Due to technical or privacy issues, archived websites may not be exact copies of the original website at the time of the web crawl. Certain file types will not be captured dependent on how they are embedded in the site. Other parts of websites that the crawler has difficulty capturing includes Javascript, streaming content, database-driven content, and highly interactive content. Full-Text searches of archived websites are available at https://archive-it.org/organizations/567.
Socialism and education |z New York (State); Alternative education -- New York (State); Manuscripts; Correspondence.; Poems.; Christian socialism |z Pennsylvania.; Christian socialism |z New York (State); Socialism and education |z Pennsylvania.; Oral histories (literary works); Alternative education |z Pennsylvania.; Manumit School (Pawling, N.Y.); Speer, R. Michael; Fincke, Benjamin; Manumit School (Bristol, Pa.); Fincke, William Mann; Dretzin, Barbara Dutton
- 2012 Addendum, 2008-2012 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- 2015 Addendum, 1952, 2012 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Book of Illustrated Stories Written by Manumit School Students Who Were Around High School Age During World War II, 1940s (Box 3)
- Chronology and Histories, 2000s (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Chronology and Alumni Correspondence, 2007-2012; 2014.104 (Box 1, Folder 2A)
- Cohn, Fannia M. Papers (Copies), 1932-1933 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence and Writings on Manumit, 1950-1956 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- E-mails, 2005-2009 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Fincke, Benjamin and Magda: Letters to, 1944-1954 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Fincke, Benjamin: In Memory of, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Fincke, Benjamin: Resignation as Co-Director, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Fincke, William Mann: Memoranda on Manumit, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Fincke, William Mann: Memorial Service, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Fincke, William Mann: "Selections from the Theory of Knowledge" [long poem], 1944 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Fincke, William Mann: Writings, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Garland Fund/American Fund for Public Service (Copies), 1924-1930 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Greenstone, Ted, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Manumit School Publications, 1928-1956 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Manumit School Website CD, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Manumit Symposium CD, 2011 July 9 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- The Manuscript, undated, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Photographs: Manumit School "Dixon-Bush" Work Program, 1949-1951 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Photographs: Manumit School Photographs from Peppy Vulliet on CD, 2000s (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Photographs: Manumit School Photographs from Scrapbook, 1947-1948 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Photographs: Manumit School Photographs from Scrapbook (Photocopies of pages), 1947-1948 (Box Shared Tamiment OS005)
- Photographs: Manumit School Reunion (CD), 2006 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Photographs, 1938-1939 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Photographs, 1948-1967 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Photographs, 1950-2004 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Photographs, 2000s (Box 2, Folder 8)
- [Reproductions, Possibly from New York Public Library and Photocopies of Manumit Brochures], 1924-1944 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Scholarship Fund Program Event, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- School Closing Materials, 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Writings, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Archived Website, Sep 2, 2009-ongoing
  Scope and Content Note
  The Manumit School was an "experimental boarding school in Pawling NY. Founded on purchased farm land in 1924 by William and Helen Fincke, it was formally call the Manumit School for Workers' Children. An early promotional flyer for the school asked parents if they'd like their children to grow up "to become men and women who can think for themselves, stand on their own two feet and fight injustice and oppression. " It's teachings were meant to provide a "progressive " "workers education" slant during a time of increasing socialist optimism in America. In 1944 the school moved to Bensalem Township, Bucks County, Pennsylvania. The school closed in 1957. This website is an informational website.